Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  - ABC: Nightline - Burma Deception, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU125)
    A Karen leader: "Oppression has been escalated, the hospital has no doctor or medicines and forced labor was used to construct the buildings."
    People got frustrated with the effort to find lasting peace.
    Poppy flowers fruit, drug traders are now at peace with SLORC.
    Timber sales occur on the border.
    Pepsi, KFC, Pizza Hut entered Burma. The opposition called for sanctions but international governments are reluctant. China is a major arms supplier.
    Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN): "Constructive engagement."
    National convention and ASEAN booths are shown.
    A child beggar.
    The elected party must be allowed to rule.
    In honor of Cynthia Jervis who gave her life, April, 1993. She died of Malaria.
  - Altsean: Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi Regarding Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:17:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU126)
    Produced by: Altsean Production
    1997
    ASEAN would not get what they expect from Burma. The economy cannot take off under the present situation. ASEAN should push the SPDC for a dialogue. An accountable and transparent government is necessary to have a feasible economic gain. Sporadic meetings are not for dialogues. I believe in cautious optimism. I am always ready for a dialogue.
    We work hard. Our offices were forced to close but people continue to work with us. Politics comes from every day work.
    I fell down the stairs but I am absolutely fine. I am married to a British citizen. I can have British citizenship anytime. I do not need a green card to go to the USA. Perhaps they want green cards.
    People motivate me the most. They know we are the powerful force in Burma. Therefore they put such restrictions on us.
  - Images Asia: Burma Ten Years On; A Parliament Denied, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:48:00] (2 copies) (Box 295 and 302, Video-cassette BU127)
    Interview conducted by Daw Aung San Suu Kyi with the National League for Democracy (NLD), CEO and committee members in May of 2000.
    Ten years after the election in which the NLD won a landslide victory, this was never honored by State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: "This is not a pre-arranged election."
    Why are people continuing to struggle for democracy in Burma? Why do we have confidence that we will win? Democracy is a human value. We want democracy because we want freedom. Security has to be balanced by freedom. Japan's good will should not be manipulated for the good of the few. The rule of law should prevail, accountable leadership should be installed."
    U Aung Shwe: "No one has the right to dismiss the people's representatives. When parliament is convened even those dismissed by the junta will have to come back. Every nation has problems. The solutions are mostly on the table."
    U Aye Tha Aung (non-member of the NLD): "We represent the ethnic groups. We demanded authority to convey the parliament but they responded with massive arrests. We are representative of the people and we have duties to fulfill. When parliament is conveyed we will tackle the ethnic problem." (He was later arrested.)
    U Hla Pe: "They tried all possible means to break the flesh and soul of the elected representatives. We can call parliament in a matter of days."
    U Tin Oo (former Chief of Staff, now the NLD Chair) speaks of civilian government rule.
    U Ohn Gyaw: "The rule of law is most important. It has to be installed. Only democracy can achieve that. We have many friends who will help us."
    U than Tun: "On the forced labor issue there has been no action on Burma. The forced labor continues."
    U Lwin: "On the issue of social and educational status. We are so far behind on the issues of government spending on education and health, on the rule of law and transparency, on accountability. Defense spending should be reduced. Our farmers' dream is to own land. Farmers are the most oppressed. Act 4/78 should be abolished, 3/63 be amended. That is our first priority."
    U Soe Mytint: Speaks about the farmers' sector.
    Naw Ohn Hla: "Believing that democracy will provide security, I joined the party. I urge people not to be afraid."
    U Naing Naing: "I believe the country needs a change. I pay my dues for the changes. I will continue to do so. I have made up my mind."
    U Htun Myint: "Voices of fear. We have to stand up for the truth."
    Ko Aye Tun: Speaks about the Youth wing. "If we have good leaders, then we will follow. One day we will win. If we love our country we have to do right. Education is still in an experimental stage."
  - ABC (Australian TV): The Edge of Burma (1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:50:00] (Box 296, Video-cassette BU128)
    Produced by: ABC Australia
    Edited by Mark Foster, Australia Sources, 40 Years War. John Pelligran, Australia. (50 Minutes)
    Life with Karen National Union (KNU), Karen people and their rebellion against the Burmese junta. The Kawthule revolution lasted for over 40 years. For identity, freedom, the Karen are prepared to fight on for even longer.
    Slogans, marches and dances symbolize a Karen celebration for the New Year in a Karen camp. The KNU explains that Burmese oppression sparked the rebellion. A Karen commander speaks: "When we meet we will fight, we will pursue and kill them. "He talks of how the regime laid land mines across the country which caused civilian causalities. A health epidemic is a problem. Blood transfusions cannot be done. The Karen will win if we trust in God. A skirmish with army troops is shown. Villagers live in the war zone. An interview takes place with POWs. The KNU motto: "In God We Trust. Only God will deliver victory."
    On the front line, gunfire and verbal abuse occur. Bo Mya: "The Karen are not Burmese but they bomb the country from us. "The River Moi border is shown between Thailand and Manaplaw which is the headquarters of the KNU.
    The Prime Minister, Saw Ba Tin: "We can never become Burmese."
    More evidence of atrocities by the army is shown. A daughter is forced to watch her father burned to death. The Burmese forces deny this.
    Burma Ten Years On; A Parliament denied. (Altsean Burma, May 2000
  - Janus Film: The Burmese Harp, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:57:00] (2 copies) (Box 296, Video-cassette BU129)
    Produced by: Kon Ichikawa/Janus Film
    Japanese, English Subtitles, 1957. Fiction.
    In Burma, soil is red. So is the rock.
    July 1945, the Japanese are losing the war in Burma. The Japanese have retreated from every front. From one unit hiding deep in the jungle is a harp-playing soldier named Mitzushima. His unit surrendered to allied forces. Commissioned to convince other units to surrender, he wandered, visiting other companies. His unit was crushed after refusing to surrender but he survived. Pretending to be a Buddhist Monk, while trying to reunite with his mother unit, he sees dead Japanese soldiers scattered about Burma. He feels responsible for burying the dead and does it single-handedly, never rejoining his company again. He stays behind in Burma although his unit leaves Burma to rejoin Japan.
  - NBC: Beyond Rangoon, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:17:00] (2 copies) (Box 296, Video-cassette BU130)
    Produced by: NBC
    Network: NBC
    Airing Program: Dateline
    Undercover mission by NBC crew into Burma, which collected information and interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi.
    Inconceivable choice for one's family or country. How precious freedom is and how high a price can be paid for it.
    Burma, Land of fear. Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, a symbol of hope.
    It was not sacrifice, it was choice because nobody forced you to do it. Colleges were closed until last week, possession of a cellphone and fax machine can cause one's imprisonment. "One can be jailed even for doing the right thing, even behaving in accordance with the law. If the authorities don't agree it can mean a jail term. Like a spy movie there are decoy calls, coded calls and hidden tapes. "Everywhere we look the army is there."
    "Two car and two cycles wait for me," Suu Kyi.
    Married in 1972 to Professor Michael Aris with two children, Alexander and Kim, Suu Kyi's life changed in 1988.
    Yusen Kin: "We never thought the government would do that, I shed a tear when I heard her. Thousands were killed. "Scene from Beyond Rangoon. She has been under house arrest for 6 years. "There was an election victory and she's still locked up."
    Michael's life without Suu. They have paid the price. "The separation is too painful to talk about."
    Tin Win, Ambassador: "She has an easy life compared to being in prison or solitary confinement. The Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to her in 1991. People should be forced to choose between a private life and political beliefs."
    Six days on a bridge. A brief appearance on Martyr's day. Her dying husband was denied visa. "He wanted to die in her arms. "Michael died March 27, 1999. "I am so fortunate to have such a wonderful husband. Nothing can take that away from me. "Suu Kyi on her husband's death. "I am not fed up."
    Tin Win: "She is just a housewife, nothing more than that. "
    She supports the US Sanction on Burma.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): October Challenges, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:40:00] (3 copies) (Box 296, Video-cassette BU131)
    Produced by: NLD, LA/Thailand
    October '99 raid of Burmese Embassy in Thailand. Free Burma News Agency, Arm of the People Studio (Burmese, 40 Minutes).
    Oct. 1, '99 Burmese Embassy in Thailand is occupied by a group of Burmese student warriors.The Junta's flag is pulled down and the NLD flag is raised.
    Students say the Junta ignored the election. This incident is an explosion of resentment against the perceived oppression. Ne Win speaks in the party Congress in 1988: "I want all of you to know you defy orders the army will always shoot straight, not in the air. "The army kills thousands in an attempt to crush the uprising. Scenes of shooting in Rangoon streets.Atrocities committed by State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
    Students come in with a guitar case loaded with guns and grenades. Bangkok is shaken by five shots of gunfire. The Thai's security nightmare. "Vigorous Burmese Student Warriors led by Johnny." Scenes of the raid. Three demands are put forth: 1. To release all political prisoners; 2. To open dialogue with NLD and CAPP; 3. To initiate emergency government. Nine shots are fired to commemorate 4 nines incident.
    Thai Prime Minister, Foreign Minister come and are advised not to use force.
    Thai ambassador meets Khin Nyunt who shows no sign of interest in the demands.
    Students did no harm and the Foreign Minister believes everything can be solved peacefully. The NLD denies all connection with the incident.
    Exiled Burmese students demand a peaceful solution. Children are under the boot of the army. Prime Minister Chuan "wishes to solve it without any bloodshed."
    Johnny promises there will be no bloodshed.
    NLD LA. U than Htut: "We have no connection at all but we understand why they have to do it." All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF)'s Moe The Zon: "They are the examples of what peoplewant."
    October 2, 1999: "Johnny demands a helicopter which is granted. "Aung Aung is arrested outside. One pregnant woman, then Sein Nyunt are released. The hostages praise the students and sympathize with them. Home Minister: "They are not terrorists. Their demands are fair."
    Prasatt, a visa applicant, comes out, demands to clear the way. Prasatt drives a van. Gunfire is heard. Two vans slow toward the school compound. Hostages run out of the compound. A chopper lands on the football grounds.
    SPDC closes the border, affecting millions of lives across the border. Bo Mya: "We will help them."
    Prasatt: "I trust them and they trusted me." Johnny demands another chopper. Deputy Foreign Minister Sugonpan: "I would go along with them." Hostages are greeted and wished freedom in Burma.
    Hands wave goodbye. The chopper lands at Bangwalay. Johnny and his team cross back to border peacefully. Sugonpan is honored. Tape 151: Shan: Burma.
  - Shan: Burma, PAL VHS [TRT 0:05:00] (Box 296, Video-cassette BU132)
    Produced by: SHAN Human Rights
    A priest and villagers in a poor situation. An order from the Army for forced laborers. The Army marches. A skirmish. Four cuts. Information, supplies, strength and reinforcement. They effectively let the people starve. An Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) meeting, 1996. A monk's hard labor on the mountain slopes.
    "Forced relocation takes place. Those who refuse are shot. "Amnesty International is concerned.
  - Amateur Footage: Rangoon, Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (3 copies) (Box 296 and 289, Video-cassette BU133)
    Produced by: Nancy Anderson, Private
    A Day in the City of Rangoon: Narrow, crowded streets. Side street vendors. Roadside snacks. Cold drink stands. People in traditional longyi.
    Sule pagoda. Worshipers sayprayers. Magnificent ancient Burmese architecture and art of curving. Buddha's replica that people worship. Paintings on the walls.
    Downtown Rangoon. Famous Bogyoke market. Jewelry shops. Gift shops. Puppet store. Faces of vendors.
    Market over the bridge: Fresh vegetables. Dried fish. Sugarcane juicer.
    Shwedagon Pagoda. A guide explains the story of Shwedagon. Shin Byu Festival. Banana branches for Gadaw Pwe. Poe Thu Daw. Big bell of Shwedagon. Five bell rings for the fulfillment of the dream.
    Karaweik Hotel: A wedding. Wedding march played.
    Kang Daw Gyi lake shore. A Damhayone. Kahtein Pwe Daw.
    Pegu Shwemawdaw: A Monastery: Interview with a monk; a prayer and a Yathe. A Chinwine.
    Burma Highway. Rice processing. Tricycle. Stop over. Young vendors and child labor. A Pagwet. Crowded buses. Nuns Methela, Kunya. Roadside eatery.
    Mounted statue of Bo Aung San. Shwe Chinthe. Bedin Sayama (fortuneteller).
    A stall in Thailand.
  - Amateur Footage: Karen Refugee Footage, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (Box 296 and 289, Video-cassette BU134)
    Produced by: Jeanne Hallacy, Private
    Displaced Karen refugees in Thai Burma border. Refugee camps in general. Children at camp school.
    Dance Practice. Children without much hope of better lives. An interview. Bath time and volleyball grounds.
  - Amateur Footage: Interviews withDr. Cynthia Maung and U Min Zin (December 5, 1999), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:60:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU135)
    Produced by: Nancy Anderson,Private
    Interview with Dr. Cynthia Maung and U Min Zin.
    Dr. Cynthia Maung: People show incredible spirit. The clinic is for internally displaced people. The students, church groups and Burmese overseas are helped first. Malaria is the main admission, as well as HIV and Tuberculosis. The patient number is growing. We have different units to treat different patients. There are more migrant workers now. Sixty others help in the clinic. Most deaths were caused by malaria, infection, malnutrition and violence.Public education is now extended.
    We are migrant workers.Medic across the border is at great risk. After the deportation the patient number is greatly reduced but there are more severe cases.
    We need to see effective and sustainable development. Suffering is growing despite hard work and prayers. Over a million are infected by HIV virus.
    We should stop the narcotic flow. Thai shows interestin working together but has put in place many restrictions. Twenty Burmese are killed everyday in Thailand. Narcotics problem grows. Thai employers do not take responsibility. There are unsafe abortions and abandoned babies. Mental health is important. Health education program is working very well. My busiest day can be from 6 am to midnight.
    Scene of the clinic: One patient says, "It is impossible to get treatment in Burma. It is too expensive and we are often ignored. A patient had to be referred to Myawaddy hospital to get diagnosis and then cameback for medication. There is absolutely no medicine in Burma for us."
    Win Win Mar: "People suffer severe illness. My father went to Bangkok and never came back."
    Serious patients.
    Min Zin (Student Activist Leader): My father spentlong time in jail. My parents showed me what is going on in my country. 1988 my sisters were arrested and I took part since June 1988. I was associated with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi. I kept underground since 1988 until 1997. People support democracy. I have to hide whenever they search. I received a lot of help from people. Working inside Burma is much meaningful. The problems: Lack of communication. Lack of space.
    Seven years jail sentence is imposed for youth that set up the library.
    Junta not ask for support only tolerance. Be more aggressive. A change can be seen in 24 hours. Demonetization broke the people's spirit.
  - Amateur Footage: Thai/Burma Border, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:20:00] (3 copies) (Box 296 and 302, Video-cassette BU136)
    Produced by: IMI file Footage (Pippa Scott)
    A refugee village along River Moi. Children digging toilets, sawing off timber to build huts. A church. A grocery store. A clinic with patients.
  - Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi regarding Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 296 and 302, Video-cassette BU137)
    Produced by: Marc Laban
    Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi regarding ASEAN
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: "Economy will not improve under present circumstances. If they want to improve economy, they must settle political problems. We do not have an accountable and transparent government to handle open market system."
    Political dialogue: "There is always cautious optimism. We are not afraid of talking to them. We work this way so they may arrest us. Dialogue is the only answer. Army should look at dialogues as the best possible solution. It should have come earlier rather than later. We also have strong support within the army. Mandate of the National League for Democracy is that any dialogue must include me."
    The State Law and Order Restoration Council cared about United States of America very much.
    U Tin Oo appeared briefly.
    State Law and Order Restoration Council did not signThe Freedom of Association Convention -- means that we are not free to form organizations without government approval.
    We are deprived of all kind of human rights. We do not have right to appeal.
    The State Law and Order Restoration Council also do not sign the convention against torture. It means we do not have right to appeal when tortured by government.
    It is not enough just by signing the convention but we must create the environment to raise the children.
    If people have to work against will it must be forced labor.
  - Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, 1996, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:35:00] (4 copies) (Box 296 and 302, Video-cassette BU138)
    Produced by: Marc Laban, Heather Kelly
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: Forced labor is nobody's tradition, although volunteer labor is practiced.
    On the UN general assembly: There are ways to implement general assembly resolutions. We have done the most we could.
    Oppression has stepped up. Offices were shut down by force, subject to a lot of pressures.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: About The State Law and Order Restoration Council, People of Burma are committed to democracy. Discuss the law in 5/96 by the State Law and Order Restoration Council.
    Bosnia conflict is the product of the strong-hand leadership.
    Right after the attack, U Tin Oo was injured.
    Su Kyi, U Kyi Maung and U Tin Oo were at roadside with a big crowd: "We're here to show our unity."
    U Kyi Maung: "About 200 fellows yelled and accused us."
    U Tin Oo: "As we left 150 USDA and criminals charged us."
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi's car was damaged. People chanted, "Good Health Daw Suu!"
    Streets of Rangoon: How Burma repairs the roads.
  - Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (4 copies) (Box 296 and 302, Video-cassette BU139)
    Sanctions: If signs of more oppression are seen then the sanctions should be tightened.
    National Convention is not the place for dialogues. Dialogues must have no preconditions.
    Market economy in Burma is chorine capitalism. Market economy profited some but for general public it is worse.
    Aung San Suu Kyi is attacked by Unity, Solidarity and Development Association (USDA), U Tin Oo injured.
  - Daw Aung San Suu Kyi Speeches, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 289, Video-cassette BU140)
    Role of leadership. Moral: lessons for the leaders. Abuse of power and cronyism that damages the country. Barbwire on the people's face. Questions and answers.
    Photo opportunity inside the house.
  - CBC (Canadian TV): Report from Rangoon, 1995, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 289, Video-cassette BU 141)
    Produced by: CBC, Heather Kelly
    Network: CBC
    Schools and education on Burma. Business in Burma. Daw Su Popularity and crack down by government. An army general: "She tired to break up the army." Michael Aris is interviewed and says: "Come what may, I will face this challenge."
  - ABC (Australian TV): Report from Rangoon, 1995, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 289, Video-cassette BU142)
    Produced by: Marc Laban for ABC, Heather Kelly
    Burma's first credit card - Myanmar Oriental Bank Card.
    Money problems: Odd notes and large amounts. Albert Young from Los Angeles. Bars and restaurants.
    Reform is cautious and controlled.
    Army's 50th anniversary - March 27, 1995.
    General Than Shwe: "Nation needs army for survival."
    State Law and Order Restoration Council. Army clashes with Hun Sa Troops at Ta Chi Leik.
    Border town Ta Che Leik.
    Asian Highway. Myawwaddy and Maesout. Friendship bridge.
    U Dorn is optimistic. Declining border trade in Maesout.
    Surging foreign investment in Burma.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi's call for sanctions on Burma.
    Regime is trying new constitution which Daw Aung San Suu Kyi rejects immediately.
    JVC's opening ceremony.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi - a challenge to junta.
    Generals refused to talk with her. Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) is welcoming State Law and Order Restoration Council. National League for Democracy withdrew from National Convention.
  - CTV: Edited Report, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 289, Video-cassette BU143)
    Produced by: Heather Kelly, CTV News
    Network: CTV
    The relocation of two Rangoon cemeteries. Colonel Hla Min "State Law and Order."
    Restoration Council's spokesman: "We have to give way for development."
    Refugees demanding relief effort. Burned villages.
    Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) Summit at Bangkok.
    Philippines President Ramos. Go Chok Taung(Singapore).
    Altsean activities.
  - ABC (Austrialian TV): Report from Rangoon, 1996, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 289, Video-cassette BU144)
    Produced by: Marc Laban for ABC
    Weekend Speeches in 1996.
    Sign of Good Kings.
    "If the king is bad, the entire nation suffers."
    During the union day celebration, the State Law and Order Restoration Council top brass show off.
    Karen rebels are at wars. Rohinger refugees. Nation would break up like Bosnia-Herzegovina.
    Best hope for Burma is Daw Aung San Suu Kyi.
    Than Shwe is at union day celebration. There are ethnic dances to honor army.
    Talk on Industries and Tourism at the Strand Hotel.
    Training for hotel staff. They say: "I'd like to see the development."